when working with documents it is
important that the content is structured
effectively windows has a number of
tools that allow you to do this and what
we're going to be looking at in this
video is the tools that you can find on
the layout tab so if we click on the
Layout tab as you can see there are
three sections here now we're primarily
going to focus on the first two which is
margins page orientation size columns
bricks and the way you can indent and
space the paragraphs around one of the
tools that were going to look at first
is the widows and orphans as you can see
it's on kicked here by default this will
be kicked in your windows program if the
widow is an orphans box isn't ticked as
you can see when I start pressing the
enter key and wolven text further down
the table and it was on to a new page it
actually allows the splitting up of
paragraphs so you can have information
starting on one lane and not finishing
till the next lane so if I just undo
what I've done there and then I select
the widows and orphans control make sure
that's ticked and select look here and
then press the Enter key again to kick
the information on in the next page you
will see that it jumps the paragraph it
won't let you have just one line on the
previous page I just don't do that
another feature that you may find useful
is the ability to keep paragraphs
together on lanes and a paragraph
together if you click on the paragraph
expansion control there as you can see
I've got keep lanes together
ticked in that box there what this means
is that when I can't press the Enter key
I move text further down the table when
it moves on to a new page it
automatically moves a whole paragraph so
it won't let you split a paragraph up
I'll just glue that back the next tool I
want to look at is the page break tool
as you can see all the information is on
one page there but there is a blank
second page but just backspace that and
not everything is on one page so for
example I wish to move the information
from this point forward onto you a new
page you go to bricks and select a page
break
now that automatically moves the
information on the page - now that's
faint but say for example I wanted to
have this page in landscape format and
keep this page in portrait form up if I
try that now so the cursor is blinking
there and change the orientation to
landscape both pages change to landscape
so I will just undo that what I need to
do here is I need to undo the pH brick
that was inserted and Roland said a page
break I need to insert a section break
next page what this does it again moves
the information on the page too but this
allows me to format this page in any way
I want so I can now select the
orientation and landscape and it will
only change that page as you can see if
I go to the Home tab and use the fuel
and hide button to see the formatting
that is being applied as you can see
that as a section brick next page so
that has basically moved everything down
and the formatting that's applied to
that the layout of that page can be
different to pH one if I remove this
show and hide click off that and then
insert another section brick next page
from the layout tab this third page can
then be changed again so for example I
could go back to poetry at fallout one
so as you can see I can have one page in
portrait one page in landscape and then
when I wish to continue with the
document I can have the third page back
in
another tool that you may find useful is
that you may present information in
column format so wrong having the text
spread all across the page you may have
a document where you need to insert it
in column format so if I place the
cursor at the front of the text on the
first page and if I look at the columns
button I click on that I can change it
to one to three columns so just as an
example I'll change that to two columns
as you can see all of the text has now
been bunched up on the left-hand side of
the page if I just insert the clears are
there and press the Enter key as you can
see it is now moving the text to another
column on the same page this can be
useful if you're presenting something
such as a newsletter as your document
increases in size it would be useful to
insert page numbers so you can identify
the pages as a document across to do
this we need to go to the insert tab so
I click on insert and as you can see I
look along to the header and footer
section there's the option to insert
page numbers so I click on the page
number and it will ask me if I wish to
place it at the top of the pH at the
bottom of the page in the margin of the
page for this one I'm just going to
select the bottom of the page and as you
can see there are a variety of
formatting that can be applied to the
way the page number is entered for this
one I'm going to simply select plain
number two and that will insert a page
number in the footer section of the
document so I'll just click away from
that and as you can see that is
automatically inserted page numbers on
the three pages within this document